# RACHEL BARTH

## VISUAL JOURNALIST | INNOVATIVE STORYTELLER

#### PORTFOLIO

rachelbarth.carbonmade.com

#### SKILLS

UX Basic Training Certification from the Nielsen Norman Group.

Expert in InDesign, Photoshop, Illustrator, WordPress, MailChimp, Premiere Pro, Acrobat, Quark XPress, Excel and Word. Proficient in After Effects.

Background in reporting, editing, blogging, photo editing, art direction and strategic branding.

## **AWARDS**

Winner of the 2014 Gold Medal for redesign of Federal Times from the American Society of Business Publication Editors.

## **EDUCATION**

#### M.S. in Journalism

Medill School of Journalism, Northwestern University Evanston, Ill.

#### **B.A.** in Writing Seminars

Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md.

## CONTACT

rachelbarth@yahoo.com 703-244-1917 Alexandria, Va.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

## Visual Editor & Director of Design, American Road and Transportation Association |

Washington, D.C.

May 2016 to present

Conceptualize and design visual materials for national association, which include a bi-monthly magazine, weekly digital newsletter, website, marketing materials for nearly a dozen annual events and daily email and social media promotions.

Achievements include a redesign of the magazine for both content and look, implementing new design standards for website and electronic communications, and establishing brand continuity between all products.

## Product Designer, Sightline Media Group |

Springfield, Va.

March 2007 to April 2016

Plan and design editorial illustrations, pages and infographics for six newspapers, two magazines and seven websites, in addition to creating visuals for digital products, ads, marketing materials and events.

Achievements include an award-winning redesign; creating and implementing new data-driven content; filming and editing a weekly online news program; designing invitations, programs and signage for our most prestigious annual company event; creating illustrations and motion graphics for our first motion graphic franchise; and partnering with a developer to re-imagine our military awards database to be an informative and visually appealing website.

#### Assistant managing editor, The Examiner Newspapers |

Washington, D.C.

June 2002 to March 2007

Managed the production desk of the daily Washington and Baltimore newspapers. Also served as fashion editor of daily section.

#### Freelance reporter and editor |

Clients included the Daily Herald (Chicago), The Community College Times and The Washington Examiner 2001-2013

#### Intern, Independent on Sunday

London, England
September to December 2001
Reporter and researcher for the home news department.

#### Reporter, Connection Publishing |

McLean, Va.

August 1998 to December 2000

Community reporter for the Potomac Almanac. Beat included county and school boards. Features writer for all the Connection newspapers.